<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "../tools/docbook-xml-4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="paraprof.3d">

  <title>3-D Visualization</title>

    <para>ParaProf displays massive parallel profiles through the use of OpenGL
    hardware acceleration through the <firstterm>3D Visualization</firstterm>
    window.  Each window is fully configurable with rotation, translation, and
    zooming capabilities.  Rotation is accomplished by holding the left mouse
    button down and dragging the mouse.  Translation is done likewise with the
    right mouse button.  Zooming is done with the mousewheel and the + and -
    keyboard buttons.</para>

  <sect1 id="paraprof.trianglemesh">
    <title>Triangle Mesh Plot</title>

    <figure> <title>Triangle Mesh Plot</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject><imagedata fileref="trianglemeshplot.gif" scalefit="0"
		       width="6in" align="center"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This visualization method shows two metrics for all functions, all
      threads.  The height represents one chosen metric, and the color,
      another.  These are selected from the drop-down boxes on the right.
    </para>

    <para>To pinpoint a specific value in the plot, move the
      <emphasis>Function</emphasis> and <emphasis>Thread</emphasis> sliders to
      cycle through the available functions/threads.  The values for the two
      metrics, in this case for <function>MPI_Recv()</function> on
      <literal>Node 351</literal>, the value is <literal>14.37</literal>
      seconds.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="paraprof.3dbarplot">

    <title>3-D Bar Plot</title>

    <figure id="paraprof.3dbarplot.figure"> <title>3-D Mesh Plot</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="3dview1.png" scalefit="0" width="6in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This visualization method is similar to the triangle mesh plot.  It
      simply displays the data using 3d bars instead of a mesh.  The controls
      works the same.  Note that in <xref linkend="paraprof.3dbarplot.figure" />
      the transparency option is selected, which changes the way in which the
      selection model operates. </para>

  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="paraprof.scatterplot">

    <title>3-D Scatter Plot</title>


    <figure> <title>3-D Scatter Plot</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="scatterplot2.gif" scalefit="0" width="6in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This visualization method plots the value of each thread along up to
      4 axes. Each axis represents a different function and  metric.  This view allows you to
      discern clustering of values and relationships between functions across
      threads.</para>

    <para>Select functions using the button for each dimension, then select a
    metric.  A single function across 4 metrics could be used, for
    example.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="paraprof.toplology">

    <title>3-D Topology Plot</title>


    <figure> <title>3-D Topology Plot</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="topology2.gif" scalefit="0" width="4in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
       <para> In this visualization, you can either define the layout with a MESP topology definition
         file or you can fill a rectangular prism of user-defined volume with rank-points in order of rank.
         For more information, please see the etc/topology directory for additional details on MESP
         topology definitions.
       </para>

        <para> If the loaded profile is a cube file or a profile from a BGB, then this visualizations
        groups the threads in two or three dimensional space using topology
        information supplied by the profile.</para>
<para>
When topology metadata is available a trial-specific topological layout may be visualized by selecting Windows->gt;3D Visualization and selecting Topology Plot on the visualization pane.
</para><para>
The layout tab allows control of the layout and display of visualized cores/processes.

</para><para>
Minimum/Maximum Visible (restricts display of nodes with measured values above/below the selected levels).  Lock Range causes the sliders to move in unison.

</para><para>
The X/Y/Z Axis sliders allow selection of planes, lines and individual points in the topology for examination of specific values in the display, listed in the Avg. Color Value field.

</para><para>
The topology selection dropdown box allows selection of either trial-specific topologies contained in the metadata, mapped topologies stored in an external file or a custom topology defined by the size of the prism containing the visualized cores.  The ... button allows selection of a custom topology mapping file while the map button allows selection of a map file (see &lt;tau2&gt;/etc/topology/README.cray_map for more information on generating map files).

</para><para>
If a Custom is selected the dimensions of the rectangular prism containing the cores are defined by the X/Y/Z axis control widgets.

</para><para>
The Events tab controls which events are used to define the color values and positions of cores/processes in the display.  For trail-specific and Custom topologies only event3(Color) can be changed.  For topologies loaded in MESP definition files all four events may be used in calculation of the topology layout.  In either case, interval, atomic or metadata values may be used to color or position points in the display.

</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="paraprof.commicationmatrix">

    <title>3-D Commication Matrix</title>

 <figure> <title>3-D Commication Matrix</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="3DCommMatrix.png" scalefit="0" width="6in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
<para>
   If a Trial has commication information (set  TAU_COMM_MATRIX=1 at runtime of your application), then you can launch the 3D Commication window as shown.
</para>
   </sect1>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "Book" "chapter")
end:
-->
