<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "../tools/docbook-xml-4.4/docbookx.dtd"> 
<chapter id="paraprof.otherdisplays">
  
  <title>Miscellaneous Displays</title>


  <sect1 id="paraprof.userevent.bargraph">
    
    <title>User Event Bar Graph</title> 
    
    <para>In addition to displaying the text statistics for User Defined
      Events, ParaProf can also graph a particular User Event across all
      threads.</para>
    
    <figure> <title>User Event Bar Graph</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject><imagedata fileref="usereventbargraph.gif" scalefit="0"
		       width="3.16in" align="center"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>This display graphs the value that the particular user event had for each thread.</para>

  </sect1>



  <sect1 id="paraprof.ledgers">
    
    <title>Ledgers</title> 
    
    <para>ParaProf has three ledgers that show the functions, groups, and user events.</para>
    
    <sect2 id="paraprof.ledgers.function">
      <title>Function Ledger</title>
	
	
	<figure> <title>Function Ledger</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="functionledger.gif" scalefit="0" width="2.76in" align="center"/> 
	  </imageobject></mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
      <para>The function ledger shows each function along with its current
	color.  As with other displays showing functions, you may right-click on
	a function to launch other function-specific displays.
      </para>
      
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="paraprof.ledgers.group">
      <title>Group Ledger</title>
      
      <figure> <title>Group Ledger</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="groupledger.gif" scalefit="0" width="2in" align="center"/> 
	  </imageobject></mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
      <para>The group ledger shows each group along with its current color.
	This ledger is especially important because it gives you the ability to
	mask all of the other displays based on group membership.  For example,
	you can right-click on the <literal>MPI</literal> group and select
	"Show This Group Only" and all of the windows will now mask to only
	those functions which are members of the <literal>MPI</literal> group.
	You may also mask by the inverse by selecting "Show All Groups Except
	This One" to mask out a particular group.
      </para>

    </sect2>


    <sect2 id="paraprof.ledgers.userevent">
      <title>User Event Ledger</title>

	<figure> <title>User Event Ledger</title>
	  <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="usereventledger.gif" scalefit="0" width="2.06in" align="center"/> 
            </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</figure>
	
      <para>
	The user event ledger shows each user event along with its current color.
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
  
	<sect1 id="paraprof.createselectivefile">
    
    <title>Selective Instrumentation File Generator</title> 
    
    <para>ParaProf can also help you refine your program performance by
		excluding some functions from instrumentation. You can select rules to
		determine which function get excluded; both rules must be true for a given
		function to be excluded. Below each function that will be excluded based
		on these rules are listed. 
		</para>
    <figure> <title>Selective Instrumentation Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject><imagedata fileref="ParaProfSelectiveFile.gif" scalefit="0"
		       width="3.16in" align="center"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <note><para>Only the functions profilied in ParaProf can be excluded. If you
		had previously setup selective instrumentation for this application the
		functions that where previously excluded will not longer be excluded.</para></note>
  </sect1>


</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "Book" "chapter")
end:
-->
