<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "../tools/docbook-xml-4.4/docbookx.dtd"> 
<chapter id="paraprof.preferences">
  <title>Preferences</title> 
  <para>Preferences are modified from
  the ParaProf Preferences Window, launched from the File menu. Preferences
  are saved between sessions in the
  <filename>.ParaProf/ParaProf.prefs</filename> 
  </para> 
  
  <sect1 id="paraprof.preferences.window"> 
    <title>Preferences Window</title>
    <para>In addition to displaying the text statistics for User Defined
      Events, ParaProf can also graph a particular User Event across all
      threads. </para> 
    <figure> <title>ParaProf Preferences Window</title>
      <mediaobject> <imageobject><imagedata fileref="preferences.gif"
				   scalefit="0" width="3.31in" align="center"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject> 
    </figure> 
    
    <para>The preferences window allows the user to modify the behavior and
      display style of ParaProf's windows.  The font size affects bar height, a
      sample display is shown in the upper-right.
    </para>
    
    <para>The Window defaults section will determine the initial settings for
      new windows.  You may change the initial units selection and whether you
      want values displayed as percentages or as raw values.
    </para>

    <para>The Settings section controls the following</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Show Path Title in Reverse - Path title will normally be
	  shown in normal order (/home/amorris/data/etc).  They can be reverse
	  using this option (etc/data/amorris/home).  This only affects loaded
	  trials and the titlebars of new windows.</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Reverse Call Paths - This option will immediately change
	  the display of all callpath functions between <literal>Root =&gt;
	    Leaf</literal> and <literal>Leaf &lt;= Root</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Statistics Computation - Turning this option on causes
	  the mean computation to take the sum of value for a function across all
	  threads and divide it by the total number of threads.  With this option
	  off the sum will only be divided by the number of threads that actively
	  participated in the sum.  This way the user can control whether or not
	  threads which do not call a particular function are consider as a
	  <literal>0</literal> in the computation of statistics.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Generate Reverse Calltree Data - This option will enable
	  the generation of reverse callpath data necessary for the reverse callpath option of the statistics tree-table window.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Show Source Locations - This option will enable the display of source code locations in event names.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1> 
  
  <sect1 id="paraprof.preferences.defaultcolors"> 
    <title>Default Colors</title> 
    
    <figure> <title>Edit Default Colors</title> <mediaobject>
	<imageobject><imagedata fileref="defaultcolors.gif" scalefit="0"
		       width="4.92in" align="center"/></imageobject> </mediaobject> 
    </figure>
    
    <para>The default color editor changes how colors are distributed to
      functions whose color has not been specifically assigned.  It is
      accessible from the File menu of the Preferences Window. 
    </para> 
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="paraprof.preferences.colormap"> <title>Color Map</title> <figure>
      <title>Color Map</title> <mediaobject> <imageobject><imagedata
	    fileref="colormap.gif" scalefit="0" width="2.54in"
	    align="center"/></imageobject> </mediaobject> </figure> 

    <para>The color map shows specifically assigned colors.  These values are
      used across all trials loaded so that the user can identify a particular
      function across multiple trials.  In order to map an entire trial's
      function set, Select "Assign Defaults from ->" and select a loaded trial.
    </para> 
    
    <para>Individual functions can be assigned a particular color by
      clicking on them in any of the other ParaProf Windows.
    </para> 

  </sect1>
  

</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "Book" "chapter")
end:
-->
