<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "../tools/docbook-xml-4.4/docbookx.dtd"> 


<chapter id="CorrelationAnalysis">
	<title>Correlation Analysis</title>
	<para>Correlation analysis in PerfExplorer is used to explore relationships
	between events in a profile.  Each event is pairwise plotted with the other
	events, and a correlation coefficient is calcuated for the relationship.
	When the events are highly positively correlated (coefficient of close to
	1.0) or highly negatively correlated (coefficient close to -1.0), then the
	relationships will show up as linear groupings in the results.  Clusters
	may also be apparent.
	</para>
    <sect1 id="DimensionReduction2">
        <title>Dimension Reduction</title>
        <para>Often, many hundreds of events are instrumented when
        profile data is collected.  Clustering works best with
        dimensions less than 10, so dimension reduction is often
        necessary to get meaningful results.  Currently, there is
        only one type of dimension reduction available in
        PerfExplorer.  To reduce dimensions, the user specifies a
        minimum exclusive percentage for an event to be considered
        "significant".
		</para>
        <para>To reduce dimensions, select the "Select Dimension
        Reduction" item under the "Analysis" main menu bar item.
		The following dialog will appear:  
        </para>
    <figure id="perfexplorer.mainwindow.dimensionreduction1b">
	<title>Selecting a dimension reduction method</title>
     <mediaobject>
     <imageobject><imagedata fileref="dimensionreduction1.gif"
	   scalefit="0" width="2in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

			<para>
			Select "Over X Percent".  The following dialog will appear:  
            </para>

    <figure id="perfexplorer.mainwindow.dimensionreduction2b">
	<title>Entering a minimum threshold for exclusive percentage</title>
     <mediaobject>
     <imageobject><imagedata fileref="dimensionreduction2.gif"
	   scalefit="0" width="2in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

			<para>
			Enter a value, for example "1".
            </para>
        </sect1>

        <sect1 id="PerformingCorrelationAnalysis">
			<title>Performing Correlation Analysis</title>
		<para>To perform correlation analysis, you first need to select a
		metric.  To select a metric, navigate through the tree of
		applications, experiments and trials, and expand the trial of
		interest, showing the available metrics, as shown in the figure
		below:
		</para>

    <figure id="perfexplorer.mainwindow.correlation"> <title>Selecting a
	Metric to Cluster</title>
     <mediaobject>
     <imageobject><imagedata fileref="clusteringselection.gif"
	   scalefit="0" width="6in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

		<para>After selecting the metric of interest, select the "Do
		Correlation Analysis" item under the "Analysis" main menu bar item.
		A confirmation dialog will appear, and you can either confirm
		the correlation request or cancel it.  After confirming the
		correlation, the analysis will begin.  When the analysis results
		are available, you can view them in the "Correlation Results" tab.
		</para>

    <figure id="perfexplorer.correlation.results"> <title>Correlation
	Results</title>
     <mediaobject>
     <imageobject><imagedata fileref="correlationresults.gif"
	   scalefit="0" width="6in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

		<para>There are a number of images in the "Correlation Results"
		window.  Each thumbnail represents a pairwise correlation plot
		of two events.  Clicking on a thumbnail image
		in the main window will bring up the images, as shown below:
		</para>

    <figure id="perfexplorer.correlation.example"> <title>Correlation
	Example</title>
     <mediaobject>
     <imageobject><imagedata fileref="correlationexample.gif"
	   scalefit="0" width="6in" align="center"/></imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

        </sect1>
</chapter>
