<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
	  "../tools/docbook-xml-4.4/docbookx.dtd"> 

 <book id="TauUsersGuide">
  <title>TAU User Guides</title>
  
  <bookinfo>
    <!-- <edition>Second</edition>
    <isbn>0-00000-000-0</isbn> -->
    <!--     <authorgroup> -->
    
    <!--       <author> -->
    <!-- 	<firstname>University of</firstname> -->
    <!-- 	<surname>Oregon</surname> -->
    <!--       </author> -->
    
    <!--     </authorgroup> -->
    
    <editor>
      <firstname>TAU</firstname>
      <surname>Team</surname>
    </editor>
    
    <!--    <pagenums></pagenums> -->
    <!--     <pubdate>2005-08-15</pubdate> -->
    
    <!-- <copyright> -->
    <!--       <year>2005</year> -->
    <!--       <holder>University of Oregon Performance Research Lab</holder> -->
    <!--     </copyright> -->

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="NewTauLogo.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    


    <legalnotice>
      <para>Updated May 4th, 2015 for use with version 2.24.1 or greater.</para>

      
      <para>Copyright &copy; 1997-2012
      Department of Computer and Information Science, University of Oregon 
      Advanced Computing Laboratory, LANL, NM 
      Research Centre Juelich, ZAM, Germany</para>
      
      <para>Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this software and
	its documentation for any purpose and without fee is hereby granted,
	provided that the above copyright notice appear in all copies and that
	both that copyright notice and this permission notice appear in
	supporting documentation, and that the name of University of Oregon (UO)
	Research Centre Juelich, (ZAM) and Los Alamos National Laboratory (LANL)
	not be used in advertising or publicity pertaining to distribution of the
	software without specific, written prior permission.  The University of
	Oregon, ZAM and LANL make no representations about the suitability of
	this software for any purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or
	implied warranty.</para>

      <para>UO, ZAM AND LANL DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
	SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
	FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE UNIVERSITY OF OREGON, ZAM OR LANL BE
	LIABLE FOR ANY SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
	WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
	ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
	OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
      </para>

    </legalnotice>



  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <para>TAU Performance System&reg;  is a portable profiling and tracing
      toolkit for performance analysis of parallel programs written in Fortran,
      C, C++, Java, and Python.
      
      TAU (Tuning and Analysis Utilities) is capable of gathering performance
      information through instrumentation of functions, methods, basic blocks,
      and statements. The TAU API also provides selection of profiling groups
      for organizing and controlling instrumentation. Calls to the TAU API are
      made by probes inserted into the execution of the application via source
      transformation, compiler directives or by library interposition.</para>

    <para>This guide is organized into different sections. Readers wanting to
      get started right way can skip to
      the <link linkend='ApplicationScenario'>Common Profile Requests</link>
      section for step-by-step instructions for obtaining difference kinds of
      performance data. Or browse the <link linkend='StartersGuide'>starters
      guide</link> for a quick reference to common TAU commands and
      variables.</para>
    

      <para>TAU can be found on the web at: <ulink
					       url="http://tau.uoregon.edu"
					       >http://tau.uoregon.edu</ulink></para>
  </preface>
    <!--<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
		href="../tutorial/tutorial.xml" />-->
    
	<part id="TAUUSERMANUAL">
	  <title>Tau User Guide</title>

   	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../taucompiler/taucompiler.xml" />
	
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../newguide/profiling.xml" />
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="../newguide/tracing.xml" />
   
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="anaylsis.xml" />
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="startersguide.xml" /> 
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../scenario/scenario.xml" /> 
	</part>
		
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../paraprof/book.xml" /> 
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../perfexplorer/perfexplorer.xml" />
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../perfdmf/book.xml" />
</book>
